Guide to the Harold Robins Papers WAG.175
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harold Robins Papers
1931-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robins, Harold
Isserman, Maurice
WAG.175
4.75 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes and 1 shared flat box.
Harold Robins (1908-1987) was a socialist and Trotskyist who served as a guard in Leon Trotsky's household from 1939-1940. He was present when Trotsky was assassinated in August 1940 and spent the rest of his life researching and writing about Trotsky's political philosophy and his assassination. The Harold Robins Papers (1931-1988) include research files, correspondence, press clippings, and writings related to Robins's allegation that members of the Socialist Workers Party, including Joseph Hansen, had been recruited by American or Soviet intelligence and helped facilitate Trotsky's assassination.
Scope and Content Note
The Harold Robins Papers (1931-1988) are made up of research files, writings, and correspondence related to the 1940 assassination of Leon Trotsky; specifically, Robins's belief that the assassination was enabled by the infiltration of Soviet and American intelligence agencies into Trotsky's inner circle. Robins believed that intelligence agencies had recruited Socialist Worker's Party (SWP) member Joseph Hansen, and most of the collection relates to Robins's work researching and defending this allegation.
The collection contains drafts of an unfinished, untitled book Robins was writing about Trotsky's assassination, his contributions to Security and the Fourth International: An Inquiry into the Assassination of Leon Trotsky, and other writings. It documents his relationships with the SWP and Joseph Hansen in party meeting minutes, correspondence, press clippings, ephemera, and writings, including a written statement accusing Joseph Hansen of being an FBI-GPU agent. Robins's membership in the Worker's League (WL) is demonstrated by writings, correspondence, records of how the WL marked the centennary of Trotsky's birth, and issues of the party newspaper Bulletin. Robins's relationship with Workers Revolutionary Party (WRP) founder Gerry Healy is closely tied to Robins's WL membership and is documented in correspondence and writings.
Robins's involvement in the Gelfand v. Smith lawsuit is documented with his notes for and transcript of his deposition and research about and suggestions for questions for SWP members. The collection also includes copies of classified FBI records on American socialists that were obtained through Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests. Other documents in the collection, including Robins's correspondence, letters to the editor, other writing drafts, and copies of socialist publications, and a transcript of Robins's interview with an interviewer identified only by the initials W.L, are not closely related to a specific project or political party, but all of them illustrate Robins's lifelong dedication to Leon Trotsky's legacy. Robins's early life is documented by US Census and military records, and the collection also includes a biographical sketch written by a friend following his death.
Biographical Note
Harold Robins (1908-1987) was a lifelong socialist and follower of Leon Trotsky. In 1939 and 1940 he served as the head guard in Trotsky's Mexico City household and was present when Trotsky was assassinated in August 1940. He spent the rest of his life researching and writing about Trotsky's political philosophy and assassination.
Robins joined the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) when it was founded in 1938 and remained a member until 1960. He left the party because he believed that prominent members, specifically Joseph Hansen and Al Glotzer, had been recruited by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), the Soviet Main Intelligence Directorate (GRU), or the State Political Directorate (GPU) and helped facilitate Trotsky's assassination. In the 1970s, Robins joined the Worker's League (WL), an American offshoot of the U.K. Workers Revolutionary Party (WRP). Through the WL, he developed a relationship with Gerry Healy, the founder of the WRP, and worked with him on the International Committee of the Fourth International to produce Security and the Fourth International: An Inquiry into the Assassination of Leon Trotsky, published in 1975. In the early 1980s, Robins was involved in expelled SWP member Alan Gelfand's lawsuit (Gelfand v. Smith) to force the U.S. Government to give Gelfand access to FBI files related to SWP members.
Robins spent his retirement in Woodville, New Hampshire, where he drafted a book about his life in the Trotskyist movement.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Maurice Isserman circa 1988. The accession number associated with this gift is 1988.020.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been grouped by topic and arranged in chronological order.
Existence and Location of Originals
Originals of Leon Trotsky's correspondence are in the Leon Trotsky Exile Papers (MS Russ 13.1), held by Harvard University.
Trotskyism -- United States.; Drafts (documents); Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940; Hansen, Joseph; Fourth International; Isserman, Maurice; Socialist Workers Party; Healy, G.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Gelfand, Alan; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999.; United States. Freedom of Information Act
- Leon Trotsky's Correspondence, 1931-1940
  - Al Glotzer, 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James Cannon, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Terrence Phelan, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mexican President Lázaro Cárdenas, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mexican Authorities, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chris Andrews, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Leon Trotsky's Writings, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1, 9)
- Joseph Hansen, 1940-1981
  - "The Attempted Assassination of Leon Trotsky" by Joseph Hansen in Fourth International, April 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Joseph Hansen Press Release regarding Trotsky's Assassination, August 21, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings on Joseph Hansen, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robins's Correspondence regarding Joseph Hansen, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robins's Statement on Joseph Hansen, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Socialist Workers Party, 1940-1976
  - Political Committee's Visit in Mexico, June 18, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "A Letter to American Negros" Campaign Brochure, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Club Executive Meeting Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Robins's Letter of Resignation, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Robins's Correspondence with the Socialist Workers Party National Committee, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Party Elections, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Healy's Big Lie", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Research Files -- People, 1958, undated
  - John H. Dunning, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Morris Lewit, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Jean van Heijenoort on Lev Davidovich, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - George Breitman, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Abraham Lincoln, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Socialist Publications, 1960-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1-3, 7-8, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 23)
- Other Writings, 1970-1986
  - "The Murder of Leon Trotsky and the Social Forces who Benefitted", circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "League for the Cover-Up of Exposed GPU Agents Gains Recruit", circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Capitalists, Crises, and Perspectives for the Socialist Revolution", 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Death Takes George Vereeken", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Let the Reader Beware", 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "View of Token Law Enforcement", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Framework of GPU Agents in the Socialist Workers Party", undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Death Squads", undated (Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 24)
- Worker's League, 1971-1977
  - Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Open Letter to Joseph Hansen", circa 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "How the GPU Killed Trotsky", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trotsky Centennary Celebrations, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bulletin Newspaper, circa 1970s (Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 20-22)
- Security and the Fourth International: An Inquiry into the Assassination of Leon Trotsky, early 1970s-1978
  - Inquiry Drafts, circa 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10-12, Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Inquiry Published Version, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Inquiry Research Files, circa 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Inquiry Press Clippings, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Socialist Workers Party regarding Inquiry, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Other Security and the Fourth International Publications, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1972-1984
  - BBC regarding The Assassination of Trotsky Film, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 4, Folder 16-19)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1978-1984 (Box 4, Folder 20-23)
  - The Sunday Times regarding Trotsky Centenary Program, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Local 892 D.C. 9, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Union Painters Bulletin, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- International Press Coverage of Joseph Hansen and Gerry Healy, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 25)
- Research Files -- Topical, 1977-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
  - New York Times coverage of Trotsky's Assassination, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - GPU and GRU Agents, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
  - Socialism in Israel and Palestine, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Catholic Church and the Vatican, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Automation and Unemployment, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Genetics, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Interview Transcript -- Robins interviewed by W.L., 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Drafts of Untitled Book, 1980-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1-8, Box 7, Folder 1-10, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Gelfand v. Smith, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20, Box 5, Folder 1-14)
- FOIA Requests -- FBI Files on Socialists, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3-9, Box 9, Folder 1-4)
- Biographical Sketch of Harold Robins by Ralph Kessler, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Military and Census Records, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)